A Guide to the Home for Needy Confederate Women Records, 1862-1997
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Home for Needy Confederate Women Records, 1862-1997
The Library of Virginia
34092
24.89 cubic feet
Home for Needy Confederate Women (Richmond, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection came to the Library of Virginia in four accessions. All have been combined and now are classified jointly under the number of the largest accession, Acc. 34092.
The original Acc. 34092 came in two parts: Transferred from the Department of General Services, Richmond, Virginia, 20 February 1990, and Gift of Mary R. Cross, Richmond, Virginia, 18 June 1991. Another large accession, Acc. 34471, was transferred from the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Richmond, Virginia, 18 July 1993.
Accession 34669, consisting of one of the Home's minutes books, 1949-1961, was transferred from the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Richmond, Virginia, on 12 May 1994. It is now filed in Series II, Box 6, Folder 6.
Accession 41124, consisting of documents largely related to the closing of the Home and relocation of residents to the Brandermill Woods facility, was transferred from the Virginia Department for the Aging, Richmond, Virginia, on 29 March 2004. The majority of its contents are filed in Series II, Box 10, Folders 17-20. The files of residents Floye Belle Crump, Mary S. Lynn, Bertha Cox Moore, Lila Lee Riddell, Mary Dorothy Wright, and Osa Lee Yates, also originally part of Acc. 41124, are filed alphabetically in the resident files of Series III.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Home for Needy Confederate Women is said to have originated with a small group of impoverished widows of Confederate soldiers living in Richmond after the Civil War. Having no other options, they combined their limited resources and set up house together. Even so, their financial situation remained grim, with residents sometimes having to salvage vegetables left over from the city market for food. Help came in 1897 from the Ladies Auxiliary of the Pickett Camp of Confederate Veterans, which raised $1,000 for the women at a benefit bazaar. In 1898, the General Assembly of Virginia followed up with a charter to "provide a home for needy wives, widows, sisters, and daughters of Confederate Sailors, Soldiers, and Marines." This action paved the way for an initial appropriation of $1,000 from the Commonwealth.
With the use of these funds and others raised by additional benefit bazaars, the women purchased a house at 1726 Grove Avenue in Richmond. When the Home opened there on 15 October 1900, it held eleven residents. Financial difficulties, which would persist throughout the life of the Home, continued to be a factor. Money came in somewhat sporadically, by means of the occasional benefit event or contribution from the state and local government. Still, partly as a result of a successful 1903 fundraising bazaar, Home trustees were able to purchase a larger house at 3 East Grace Street in 1904.
The Home could easily have folded altogether in these early years were it not for the work of Elizabeth "Betsy" Lyne Hoskins Montague (1868-1951), wife of Andrew Jackson Montague (1862-1937), a governor of Virginia (1902-1906) and U.S. Congressman. Taking the cause on her shoulders, Mrs. Montague championed the Home in a variety of arenas, including the Virginia legislature, United Daughters of the Confederacy (U.D.C.) gatherings throughout the state and nation, and personal meetings with East Coast philanthropists. Working initially as the Home's acting president (under President Mary Custis Lee, daughter of General Robert E. Lee), and then as president, she served the institution for some fifty-two years.
One of Mrs. Montague's early, critical accomplishments was to secure annual funding from the Commonwealth. After her 1915 plea to the General Assembly, the Home began receiving yearly appropriations that continued to be granted into the 1980's. Another hallmark of her service to the Home was her push to build a larger, safer, and more impressive residence for the women. Pointing to damage from a 1916 fire at the Grace Street home, an ever-growing pool of applicants, and a humanitarian duty to "the Women of the Sixties," Mrs. Montague launched a major fundraising campaign. She used the opportunity to voice her intense frustration--with the U.D.C. in particular--for what she regarded as a useless fixation with building monuments. The brochure for the Memorial Building and Endowment Fund Campaign reflected this viewpoint, rejecting the value of monuments of "cold and unfeeling stone," and urging support for "an active and ever-living SERVICE, for which there is an increasing and imperative need."
Succumbing to Mrs. Montague's persuasiveness, the Robert E. Lee Camp No. 1, United Confederate Veterans, offered a two and one-half acre tract of land on the site of its soldier home. The grant, which had to be approved by the Commonwealth as the actual owners of the property, was ratified in the General Assembly on 28 January 1926. As part of the agreement, the Home was constrained to accept only wives, widows, daughters, and sisters of Confederate veterans. This would become problematic over the years as the Home struggled to fill its rooms with this dwindling demographic, while having to turn away numerous applications from granddaughters and other female descendants.
With a variety of fundraising events, speeches, and personal appeals, Mrs. Montague made the proposed building a reality, in large part due to a $250,000 bequest from Dr. Alexander Spiers George (d. 1929). Construction began on the new residence at 301 N. Sheppard Street in 1931. It opened on 23 May 1932, with space for approximately 100 residents. Somewhat ironically, architect Merrill Lee built the new Home for Needy Confederate Women to mirror the north facade of the White House, and was allowed rare access to James Hoban's original plans for the design.
In spite of Mrs. Montague's exhaustive work for the Home, she still faced criticism from outside observers. One major flap involved the General Assembly's 1944 move to reduce the pensions paid to Home residents. Local newspapers printed allegations that Mrs. Montague led the House Finance Committee to the decision by suggesting that the pensions were unnecessary. She was further accused of ordering residents not to speak of the affair to the media, under penalty of expulsion from the Home.
Mrs. Montague's most vocal opponent in the matter, Delegate C. G. Quesenbery, went on to question the Home's admission policies. A long-standing rule mandated the surrender of each resident's assets to the Home upon entrance. Quesenbery charged that the Board gave preference in the selection process to those women who could provide a $5,000 "bedroom endowment," thereby betraying the stated mission of providing for the truly indigent. In 1946, the General Assembly formed a commission to determine whether the Commonwealth should continue funding the Home. The resulting 1947 report recommended that applications be accepted on a "first come, first served" basis, and further reiterated that only wives, widows, daughters, and sisters were entitled to state support.
With this incident behind her, Mrs. Montague stayed on as president until just before her death in 1951. One of her daughters, Janet Montague Nunnally (1895-1977), then took over as president of the Home. Mrs. Nunnally held the position until health reasons forced her to resign in late 1976. Taking up the family calling, Mrs. Nunnally's daughter Janet Roy Burhans succeeded her as president. She would see the Home through its final years.
While the financial situation of the Home had always been troubled, it was set on the path of ultimate collapse in the late 1970's and early 1980's. The combination of state funds, limited private donations, and the interest from the Home endowment could no longer cover expenses, and trustees were forced to pull from the endowment itself. Eventually, it became necessary to overstep the Commonwealth's "wife, widow, daughter, or sister" qualification to bring in new residents. In 1977, the Board altered its constitution to allow other lineal descendants to enter. This prompted the General Assembly to discontinue the Home's annual funding after the 1982 fiscal year. Home representatives continued to plead for assistance and were rewarded with another round of appropriations by the 1986 General Assembly. However, the money was not renewed in the next legislative session.
As the number of residents steadily decreased, maintaining the largely unoccupied, aging building became illogical and next to impossible. On 13 April 1989 the Board voted unanimously to close the Home and continue providing for the remaining residents in a private nursing home. Before the plan could be executed, 98-year-old resident Lila Lee Riddell filed a lawsuit attempting to prevent the move. She took her appeal as far as the Virginia Supreme Court but was unsuccessful. The Court ruled that the Home's agreement with its residents only guaranteed care and shelter, not tied to a specific location.
Following a plea from Home trustees, the 1989 General Assembly set aside funds to cover any expenses for the ladies' care that could not be met by the interest on the endowment fund. The Home's final seven residents, including Lila Lee Riddell, moved into the Brandermill Woods Health Care Center in nearby Chesterfield County in August 1989. The house and grounds reverted to the Commonwealth, which set them aside for the use of the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts.
Osa Lee Yates (1898-1997), daughter of a Confederate soldier and the last surviving resident of the former Home for Needy Confederate Women, died on 30 April 1997, just short of her 99th birthday.
Scope and Content
Records, 1862-1997, of the Home for Needy Confederate Women of Richmond, Virginia, include correspondence; Board meeting minutes; the Home charter, by-laws, rules and regulations; estate files consisting mainly of wills and court documents; Home histories; guest registers; various documents pertaining to state oversight of the Home; fundraising literature; individual files and collective notebooks containing information on residents and applicants; bills and receipts; ledgers; audit reports; endowment fund and investment statements; copies of relevant state legislation; documents pertaining to various properties owned by the Home; general infirmary records and individual patient files; newspaper clippings; photographs and drawings; and miscellaneous other files including a small group of letters written by Confederate President Jefferson Davis (1808-1889) and reproductions of the controversial "Dahlgren Papers."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Administrative files
Series III. Resident and application files
Series IV. Financial records
Series V. Property files
Series VI. Medical files
Series VII. Other files
Series VIII. Photographs and drawings
Contents List
- I. Correspondence, 1893-1991 (Box 1-5)
  Most of the correspondence in this series is of a routine nature, often brief letters accompanying donations or responding to fund solicitations, expressing interest in the Home's welfare, or giving updates on work done by Board members. While the Home's relationship with the U.D.C. was often contentious, that group's constituency was also one of the Home's steadiest sources of donations. Most of the letters from U.D.C. contacts relate to contributions and friendly visits, with only occasional references to any disputes. Other correspondence can be found scattered among relevant files in other series, including letters about the 1989 relocation of the Home's last residents to Brandermill Woods, Series II; letters requesting admission to the Home, Series III; and communications regarding the Home's stock and bond holdings, Series IV. Correspondents include members of the Home's leadership, such as Presidents Mary Custis Lee (1835-1918), Elizabeth (Mrs. A.J.) Montague, Janet Montague Nunnally, and Janet Burhans; treasurers Alice A. (Mrs. A.J.) Pyle (b. ca. 1857), Rosabelle (Mrs. Emanuel) Raab (b. 1858), B. Randolph Wellford (d. 1936), Mary Parker Steinlein (b. ca. 1893), and Charles E. A. Knight; and superintendants Eloise Lipscomb (b. 1906) and Holly DeJarnette.
  - General, 1893, 1896-1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - General, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - General, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - General, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - General, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General, 1917-1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General, 1926-1930 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General, 1945-1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General, 1960, 1962-1964, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - General, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - General, 1980, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General, 1985-1989, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General, undated, from Mary Custis Lee (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General, undated, miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - General, undated, to Mrs. A.J. Montague (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - General, undated, to Mrs. A.J. Pyle (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1901-1903 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1916-1917 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1920, 1923, 1925, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1930-1932, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - U.D.C. contacts, 1977, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - U.D.C. contacts, undated (Box 5, Folder 14-16)
- II. Administrative files, 1897-1997 (Box 6-13)
  A good portion of the Home's administrative history is covered by means of Board meeting minutes, some in finalized drafts, others in note form. Other items include the Home's charter, by-laws, rules and regulations; some general histories of the institution; files on the settlement of various estates in which the Home had some interest; guest registers; dealings with various state agencies; and documentation of the Home's 1989 closing and relocation of residents to Brandermill Woods.
  - Annual reports of the Home, 1909-1911 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Application regulations (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Attempt to obtain Landmark/Historic Place designation, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Benefit concert tickets, 1904, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Board meetings--Minerva Hutchings matter, 7 April 1911 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Board meetings--Minutes book, 1917-1932 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Board meetings--Minutes book, 1933-1945 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Board meetings--Minutes book (typed), 1949-1961 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1941, 1944-1949 (intermittent) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1953-1955 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1961-1965 (intermittent) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1970 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1971 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1974 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1977 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1979 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1980 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1981 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1987 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1988 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Board meetings--Minutes, reports, etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Board meetings--Notes, ca. Oct. 1910 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Board meetings--Report by Mrs. A.J. Montague, 4 Jan. 1912 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Board member/officer lists, 1950-1984 and undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Broadside, Will Build a Home, 29 Mar. 1897 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - By-laws, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Call for resignation of Board member Mrs. Peter J. White, 1913 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Charter amendments (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Charter, By-laws, Rules and Regulations Governing the Home for Needy Confederate Women (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  - City of Richmond, burial plots and fees, 1951, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - City of Richmond, miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - City of Richmond, restaurant permits, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - City of Richmond, sanitary inspection reports, 1966, 1973-1975, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Concern over management of the Home, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Controversy over selection of Board 1st Vice President, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Court precedent in cases of vaguely-worded wills (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Dispute with George E. Pickett Camp of Confederate Veterans, 1904 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Employee leave policies and wages, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Estate files--Branin, Budd (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Estate files--George, Dr. Alexander Spiers (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Estate files--Gordon, John W. (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Estate files--Hierholzer, Alice (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Estate files--Johnson, Harriet (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Estate files--Jones, Alexander Campbell (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Estate files--Mozier, Katherine (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Estate files--Nott, Adele (Hibernia Nott v. Mary W. Nott, et. als.) (Box 9, Folder 25-26)
  - Estate files--Roy, C. Dunbar (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Estate files--Taylor, Sarah W. (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Fundraising speeches, Mrs. A.J. Montague (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - General Assembly reduction of widow pension, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Guest register, 1932-1938 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Guest register, 1939-1947, 1958-1959 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Histories of the Home (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - In Memory of the Heroes in Gray, Home fundraising booklet, ca. 1929 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Instructions for Home secretary, 1970 and undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Insurance papers, 1935-1958, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Mabel A. Taylor v. Home for Needy Confederate Women, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Master facility inventory survey, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Menu (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Monthly activity calendars, Nov. 1980-Feb. 1987 (Oversize) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - OSHA record-keeping requirements, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlets (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Permit to purchase alcohol, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Policies and procedures, 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Poster contest brochure, 1928 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Proposed takeover of the Home by the United Daughters of the Confederacy, ca. 1910-1913 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Receipts for advertisements in Benefit programme, 23 Nov. 1904 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Relocation to Brandermill Woods, 1989-1997 (Box 10, Folder 17-20)
    See also the individual files for the affected residents, filed alphabetically in Series III.
  - Rules and regulations (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy donation of cemetery plots, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - United Sons of Confederate Veterans call for support of Home (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Department of Labor/Virginia Employment Commission survey, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Updates to Commonwealth re: new residents and deaths, 1950-1953 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Updates to Commonwealth re: new residents and deaths, 1954-1959 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Updates to Commonwealth re: new residents and deaths, 1960-1963 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Updates to Commonwealth re: new residents and deaths, 1964-1966 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Updates to Commonwealth re: new residents and deaths, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Updates to Commonwealth re: new residents and deaths, 1970-1974 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Updates to Commonwealth re: new residents and deaths, 1975-1978, 1980-1982 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Virginia. Department of Health. Re: Status of Home infirmary, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Virginia. Department of Public Welfare, reports to, 1935-1945 (intermittent) (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Virginia. Department of Social Services, licensure by, 1983-1988 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Virginia. Department of Welfare and Institutions, 1951-1974 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Virginia. Department of Welfare, 1974-1982 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Virginia. State Corporation Commission, annual reports to, 1957, 1960-1963 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Virginia. State Corporation Commission, annual reports to, 1970-1989 (Box 13, Folder 18)
- III. Resident and application files, 1900-1997 (Box 14-27)
  Individual resident files typically include the woman's application, limited correspondence, and papers pertaining to any assets she may have had. The Home also kept several notebooks with basic information about the various residents, such as dates of birth and entrance to the Home, Confederate lineage, and next-of-kin. Similar files and notebooks, along with waiting lists and letters inquiring about admission to the Home offer additional information about applicants to the Home. Medical files for a number of the residents can be found in Series VI.
  - 1. Resident files, ca. 1917-1997 (Box 14-21)
    - Log of residents making admission deposits, ca. 1971-1986 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Register of resident deaths, 1926-1975 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Resident files: Abell-Ainslie (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Resident files: Alexander-Andrick (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Resident files: Applewhite-Ayres (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Resident files: Bagby-Bass (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Resident files: Bell-Boschen (Box 14, Folder 7)